Guide to the Underhill Moore Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Underhill Moore papers
1870-1948
1925-1943
MS 356
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
18
The papers consist of correspondence, course materials, diaries, legal documents, printed material, reports, subject files, and writings that document Underhill Moore's career as a law professor and his personal life. The papers emphasize Moore's teaching, writing, and involvement with Columbia Law School, Yale Law School, and the Institute of Human Relations at Yale University from 1924 to 1943. The papers also contain materials relating to Dr. William O. Moore and the Abraham Underhill estate.
Moore, Wm. Underhill (William Underhill), 1879-1949
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Underhill Moore, 1946-1948.
Biographical / Historical
William Underhill Moore was born on May 25, 1879, in New York City. He received three degrees from Columbia University: B. A. (1900), M. A. (1901), and LL.B. (1902). After graduation from law school, Moore worked briefly as an attorney in private practice and taught a course in mining law at Columbia University in 1906. Later in the same year, he obtained an appointment as a professor of law at the University of Kansas. In 1908, he left to join the law faculty at the University of Wisconsin where he taught courses in bankruptcy, insurance, negotiable interests, and property. He spent two years at the University of Chicago before returning to Columbia University in 1916.
At Columbia, Moore continued to teach courses relating to commercial transactions and was particularly well known for his expansive approach to legal instruction. His broad view that legal education should encompass the study of other social sciences (economics, sociology, and psychology), as well as conventional legal analysis, led to a division among faculty members in the late 1920s. As the situation at Columbia deteriorated, Moore sought an environment where he could explore his research interests and continue to teach.
In 1929, he accepted an appointment as Sterling Professor of Law and as a faculty member of the Institute of Human Relations at Yale University. The Institute had been formally established earlier that year as an interdisciplinary center for cooperative research and advocated intellectual collaboration among different academic disciplines. Moore received funding and assistance from the Institute throughout his years at Yale University. Moore remained on the faculty at the Law School and the Institute until his retirement in 1946. He taught intermittently at Ohio State University until his death in 1949.
Moore's most significant legal education publication was Cases on the Laws of Bills and Notes, which he co-authored with Howard L. Smith through three editions between 1910 and 1932. In addition, he wrote a series of highly regarded articles relating to banking practices that appeared in the Yale Law Review in the early 1930s. He collaborated with T. H. Sanders and Henry R. Hatfield to produce two publications for the American Institute of Accountants: Statement of Accounting Principles and Relationship Between Legal and Accounting Concepts of Capital. Moore's work at the Institute of Human Relations focused upon the effect of enforcement of parking laws upon the behavior of drivers in New Haven, Connecticut. The decade-long study culminated in the publication with Charles C. Callahan of Law and Learning Theory: A Study in Legal Control (commonly known as the New Haven parking study) in 1943.
Underhill Moore and his wife, Henelia Wilhelmi, had two children, Alwine Jane and Kent. He died in 1949 in Ohio.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, course materials, diaries, legal documents, printed material, reports, subject files, and writings that document Underhill Moore's career as an academic and his personal life. The Correspondence Series is the most voluminous and contains large amounts of intermixed professional and personal correspondence and related materials. The Personal and Family Papers focus upon the Moore Family and the strong role that Moore played in lives of his children and extended family. The voluminous and detailed nature of the papers which span fifty years provide substantial evidence of Moore's evolving roles as law student, practicing attorney, and law professor in his professional life and as an ardent suitor, husband, and father in his personal life.
Moore's writings are highlighted by Law and Learning Theory: A Study in Legal Control, which represents the culmination of a decade's study by Moore and his colleague Charles C. Callahan at the Institute of Human Relations at Yale University of the effect of automobile parking law enforcement upon driver behavior. Although the collection does not contain any preliminary data developed during the study, there are two different drafts of the book in the Writings Series.
The Underhill Moore Papers were processed as part of a collaborative effort between Manuscripts and Archives and the Yale Law School to document the careers and accomplishments of law school faculty and alumni.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Banks and banking -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Behaviorism (Psychology); Families; Law teachers; Law -- Psychological aspects; Lawyers; Ocean travel; Diaries; Educators; Lawyers; Callahan, Charles C.; Moore, Wm. Underhill (William Underhill), 1879-1949; Moser, Theodore P.; Underhill, Abraham; Columbia University. School of Law; Yale Law School; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Institute of Human Relations
- Correspondence, 1902-1943, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes both correspondence and other materials created or collected by Moore in both his personal and professional capacities. The correspondence is largely routine. It ranges from his requests for household chores to be done at his vacation home in Vermont to correspondence with colleagues about law school curriculum changes.
  Moore's original filing arrangement has generally been retained. Moore filed his correspondence by the last name of the correspondent rather than by the name of the organization or the office held by the correspondent. From 1902 to 1935, Moore filed correspondence chronologically by year, then alphabetically by the first letter of the last name of the correspondent. From 1936 to 1943, the system became more refined as Moore assigned separate folders to some individuals. The researcher should review both the general alphabetical folders and specific name folders to locate all correspondence relating to an individual. In addition, the researcher should be alert to the possibility that materials relating to the same topic may be collocated in more than one series in this collection. For example, materials relating to the administration of the estate of his maternal grandfather, Abraham Underhill, may be found in this Series under the name of the attorney for the estate (Daniel Burke) and in Series V under "Abraham Underhill estate."
  Correspondents include Arthur L. Bowley, William O. Douglas, H. R. Hatfield, Mark A. May, T. H. Sanders, Charles Seymour, Harlan Fiske Stone, and fellow faculty members. There are also materials relating to the fiduciary arrangement that Austro-German anthropologist Richard Thurnwald made with Underhill Moore to provide monetary disbursements when Thurnwald and his wife returned to Nazi-controlled Germany in 1933.
  The administrative files and faculty meeting minutes from Yale Law School chronicle the changes in curriculum and student demographics caused by World War II.
  Records from the National War Labor Board document Moore's civilian service as a mediator during World War II.
  - A
    - 1902-1906, 1921-1932 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 17)
    - 1933-1943, n. d. (Box 2, Folder 18 - 23)
  - Aaronson, Moses J., 1938-1939, n. d. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - American Appraisal Company, 1938, n. d. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - American Institute of Accountants, 1938-1939, n. d. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - American Institute Publishing Co., Inc., 1937-1939, n. d. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - American Philosophical Society, 1936-1937, n. d. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - American Sociological Society, 1938, n. d. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - American Statistical Society, 1938-1939, n. d. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Arnold, Lord, 1936-1938 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Ascher, Charles S., 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Association for Symbolic Logic, 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - B
    - 1903-1906, 1920-1928, n. d. (Box 3, Folder 34 - 46)
    - 1929-1943, n. d. (Box 4, Folder 47 - 56)
  - Bostrum, Loretta, 1942, n. d. (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Bowley, Agatha and Arthur L., 1936-1938, n. d. (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Bradford, Armory H., 1937-1939, n. d. (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Bureau of Appointments, 1936-1937, n. d. (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Burgess, Kenneth F., 1938-1939, n. d. (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Burke & Burke, 1937-1943, n. d. (Box 5, Folder 62 - 63)
  - C
    - 1902-1908, 1920-1921, n. d. (Box 5, Folder 64 - 72)
    - 1922-1930, n. d. (Box 6, Folder 73 - 82)
    - 1931-1943, n. d. (Box 7, Folder 83 - 92)
  - Carniege Corporation, 1937-1938, n. d. (Box 8, Folder 93)
  - Child family, 1937-1939, n. d. (Box 8, Folder 94)
  - Coan, Philip, 1938-1943, n. d. (Box 8, Folder 95 - 96)
  - Cohen, 1937-1939, n. d. (Box 8, Folder 97)
  - Commercial Bank Credit class, 1937-1939, n. d. (Box 8, Folder 98)
  - D, 1903-1907, 1921-1943, n. d. (Box 8, Folder 99 - 121)
  - Dennis, O.W. L., 1937-1939 (Box 9, Folder 122)
  - Dewey, John, 1937-1939, n. d. (Box 9, Folder 123)
  - Dobbs, Merrill, 1937-1943, n. d. (Box 9, Folder 124 - 125)
  - Douglas, William O., 1937-1943, n. d. (Box 9, Folder 126 - 127)
  - E, 1905-1906, 1920-1943, n. d. (Box 9, Folder 128 - 148)
  - Ebersole, J. F., 1937-1939 (Box 9, Folder 149)
  - F, 1903, 1920-1943, n. d. (Box 10, Folder 150 - 167)
  - Finlay, Stuart W., 1937-1939, n. d. (Box 11, Folder 168)
  - First National Bank and Trust Company, 1937-1943, n. d. (Box 11, Folder 169 - 170)
  - G, 1904-1906, 1920-1943, n. d. (Box 11, Folder 171 - 191)
  - Golenbock, Justin M., 1941-1942 (Box 11, Folder 192)
  - H
    - 1902-1906, 1921-1934 (Box 12, Folder 193 - 210)
    - 1935-1943, n. d. (Box 13, Folder 211 - 214)
  - Harrar, J. A., 1940-1943, n. d. (Box 13, Folder 215)
  - Haskins & Sells Foundation, Inc., 1937-1939, n. d. (Box 13, Folder 216)
  - Hatfield, H. R., 1937-1939, n. d. (Box 13, Folder 217)
  - Hope, Theodore S. Jr., 1940-1943, n. d. (Box 13, Folder 218)
  - I, 1902-1906, 1920-1940, n. d. (Box 13, Folder 219 - 232)
  - J, 1905, 1920-1943, n. d. (Box 14, Folder 233 - 252)
  - K
    - 1902-1907, 1920-1928, n. d. (Box 14, Folder 253 - 266)
    - 1929-1943, n. d. (Box 15, Folder 267 - 276)
  - Keener portrait, 1928, n. d. (Box 15, Folder 277)
  - Kocourek, Albert, 1940-1941, n. d. (Box 15, Folder 278)
  - L, 1902-1907, 1921-1943, n. d. (Box 16, Folder 279 - 301)
  - M
    - 1902-1907, 1920-1933, n. d. (Box 17, Folder 302 - 321)
    - 1934-1943, n. d. (Box 18, Folder 322 - 325)
  - Maloney, Francis T., 1940-1943, n. d. (Box 18, Folder 326)
  - May, Mark A., 1937-1939, n. d. (Box 18, Folder 327)
  - N, 1903-1907, 1920-1943, n. d. (Box 18, Folder 328 - 348)
  - National War Labor Board, 1940-1943, n. d. (Box 18, Folder 349 - 350)
  - O, 1920-1943, n. d. (Box 19, Folder 351 - 368)
  - P, 1903-1904, 1921-1943, n. d. (Box 19, Folder 369 - 388)
  - Pratt, Frank G., 1940-1942, n. d. (Box 19, Folder 389)
  - R, 1902-1907, 1921-1943, n. d. (Box 20, Folder 390 - 412)
  - Rathbone, Robert C., 1937-1943, n. d. (Box 20, Folder 413 - 414)
  - S
    - 1905-1906, 1920-1935, n. d. (Box 21, Folder 415 - 432)
    - 1936-1943, n. d. (Box 22, Folder 433 - 435)
  - Sanders, T. H., 1937-1939, n. d. (Box 22, Folder 436)
  - Seymour, Charles, 1937-1939, n. d. (Box 22, Folder 437)
  - Shanks, Carrol M., 1940-1943, n. d. (Box 22, Folder 438)
  - T
    - 1902-1907, 1920-1934, n. d. (Box 22, Folder 439 - 458)
    - 1935-1943, n. d. (Box 23, Folder 459 - 462)
  - Thurnwald, Richard C., 1933-1943, n. d. (Box 23, Folder 463 - 465)
  - Twirago, estate of Andy, 1941, n. d. (Box 23, Folder 466)
  - U, 1903-1904, 1919-1943, n. d. (Box 23, Folder 467 - 486)
  - V, 1921-1942, n. d. (Box 24, Folder 487 - 498)
  - W
    - 1902-1906, 1921-1930, n. d. (Box 24, Folder 499 - 512)
    - 1931-1943, n. d. (Box 25, Folder 513 - 520)
  - West Publishing Company, 1940-1943, n. d. (Box 25, Folder 521)
  - Y, 1920-1941, n. d. (Box 25, Folder 522 - 533)
  - Yale law school administration, 1937-1943, n. d. (Box 26, Folder 534 - 535)
  - Yale law school faculty meeting minutes, 1937-1942, n. d. (Box 26, Folder 536 - 538)
  - Z, 1923-1933 (Box 26, Folder 539)
- Subject Files, 1888-1937, Series II
  The subject files consist largely of records created when Moore was involved in private practice in the first decade of the twentieth century, and his tenure at the University of Wisconsin. The records include correspondence, notes, legal documents, opinions, receipts, and reports.
  The Series is arranged alphabetically by topic with the vast majority of files listed under the heading "Law Practice." These files are arranged chronologically and original folder titles have generally been retained.
  - Case law reports, [1904] (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Institute of Human Relations, 1937 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Law practice
    - David Dows Sr., estate of, 1888, 1904-1905, n. d. (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - West-Reed agreement, 1894, n. d. (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Linda Dows Cooksey (David Dows estate tax), 1901-1905, n. d. (Box 27, Folder 5 - 6)
    - McClelland v. English, 1902-1904, n. d. (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Street sweeper cases, 1902, n. d. (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Warner v. James, 1902-1905, n. d. (Box 27, Folder 9 - 11)
    - Belasco v. Fallert, 1903-1904, n. d. (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - Blume v. Interurban Street Railway Co., 1903 (Box 28, Folder 13)
    - James McKenna v. Susan S. Johnson, 1903, n. d. (Box 28, Folder 14)
    - Kellock-Eames (Richardson property), 1903-1904 (Box 28, Folder 15)
    - Smyth v. Western Zinc Company et. al., 1903, n. d. (Box 28, Folder 16)
    - Stewart (patent extension), 1903-1904, n. d. (Box 28, Folder 17)
    - Nathan Clark estate (Guardian of Gladys Clark, minor), 1903-1905, n. d. (Box 28, Folder 18)
    - Daiker v. Senyard, 1904, n. d. (Box 28, Folder 19)
    - Fallert v. Seidenberg, 1904-1905, n. d. (Box 28, Folder 20)
    - Harding, 1904-1905, n. d. (Box 28, Folder 21)
    - J. J. McKenna & Bro. (Hall), 1904, n. d. (Box 28, Folder 22)
    - McKenna v. Springer, 1904, n. d. (Box 29, Folder 23)
    - Smith v. First Bank of Finleyville, Pa.; Smith v. Altonwood Park, 1904-1905, n. d. (Box 29, Folder 24)
    - Vallert v. Borbe, 1904 (Box 29, Folder 25)
    - Vallert (Deutschen Kreiger Bundes), 1904 (Box 29, Folder 26)
    - Varick Securities Company v. Hutchison Acoustic Company (James J. McKenna), 1904-1906, n. d. (Box 29, Folder 27)
    - Hill-Pierson and Nassau Beekman Co. v. Sheffield and Tischan, 1905, n. d. (Box 29, Folder 28)
    - McKenna (Noble title), 1905, n. d. (Box 29, Folder 29)
    - J. J. McKenna & Bro., 1905-1906, n. d. (Box 29, Folder 30 - 31)
    - James J. McKenna v. The Jones Electric Manufacturing Company, 1905, n. d. (Box 29, Folder 32)
    - Jas. J. McKenna & Bro. Collections II, 1905-1906, n. d. (Box 29, Folder 33 - 34)
    - Montgomery title, 1905, n. d. (Box 30, Folder 35)
    - Louis D. Ray (Headmaster of Irving School), 1905, n. d. (Box 30, Folder 36)
    - In re Harlin-McNab & Harlin Mfg. Co., 1906, n. d. (Box 30, Folder 37)
    - William P. Johnston will, 1906 (Box 30, Folder 38)
    - Catherine L. M. Simons (Kraft and Geller mortgages), 1906, n. d. (Box 30, Folder 39)
    - Trowbridge v. Troy and New England Railway Co. (In the matter of Della Galusha), 1906 (Box 30, Folder 40)
    - John C. Freeman estate-Charlotte Freeman Leonard estate, 1911-1913 (Box 30, Folder 41)
    - Conway v. Zender, Circa 1913 (Box 30, Folder 42)
    - Tuppman-Thurlow Co.v. Drueding Bros. Co., 1920-1922, n. d. (Box 30, Folder 43)
    - In the matter of Joseph D. Sugarman (E. A. Gilmore), 1920-1922, n. d. (Box 30, Folder 44)
  - Memoranda of law-miscellaneous cases, 1902- 1905, n. d. (Box 30, Folder 45)
  - New York State Bar examination, 1899-1903, n. d. (Box 31, Folder 46)
  - New York State National Guard, 71stRegiment, 1894-1904, n. d. (Box 31, Folder 47)
  - Portland cement manufacturers study, 1924-1925, n. d. (Box 31, Folder 48)
  - University of Wisconsin
    - College of Agriculture-stallion laws, 1910-1911, n. d. (Box 31, Folder 49)
    - Fraternity investigation, 1910, n. d. (Box 31, Folder 50)
    - Wisconsin Engineering Journal Association, 1912, n. d. (Box 31, Folder 51)
  - Veblen, Thorstein portrait fund, 1933-1934, n. d. (Box 31, Folder 52 - 56)
  - Wisconsin lien statutes, 1909, n. d. (Box 31, Folder 57)
- Writings, 1901-1943, Series III
  This Series only contains materials relating to two of Moore's writings: an Albany Law Journal article entitled "What Constitutes A Contract?" published in 1901 and the interdisciplinary study of the effect of automobile parking law enforcement upon driver behavior entitled Law and Learning Theory: A Study in Legal Control (commonly known as the New Haven traffic study) published in 1943. Law and Learning Theory was the culmination of a decade's work by Moore and his colleague Charles C. Callahan at the Institute of Human Relations. Although the Series does not contain any preliminary data developed during the study, there are two drafts of the book.
  Also included in this series are writings by three of Moore's students-Armory H. Bradford, Theodore P. Moser, and C. R. Vance-relating to banking or early colonial law.
  - Law and Learning Theory: A Study in Legal Control-(Draft I), [1943] (Box 32, Folder 1 - 2)
  - Law and Learning Theory: A Study in Legal Control-(Draft II), [1943] (Box 32, Folder 3 - 4)
  - "What Constitutes A Contract", [1901] (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Writings of others
    - Bradford, Armory H.-"Banker's Lien", [1938] (Box 33, Folder 6 - 7)
    - Moser, Theodore P.-"History of New Haven Banks", [1933] (Box 33, Folder 8 - 9)
    - Vance, C. R.-"The Law of New Plymouth Colony", 1941 (Box 33, Folder 10)
- Law School Course Materials, 1902-1938, Series IV
  The materials in this series consist primarily of course overviews, case notes, and final examination questions prepared by Moore and other faculty members from law schools where Moore taught early in his career, but also contain two folders related to his later work at Columbia Law School and Yale Law School.
  The materials are arranged alphabetically by the name of the Law School and then alphabetically by course title.
  - Columbia University
    - Bills & notes, 1928 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Mining law, [1909] (Box 34, Folder 2 - 3)
  - University of Chicago
    - Damages, 1906-1914 (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - Mortgages, 1903-1915 (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - Suretyship, 1905, 1908 (Box 34, Folder 6)
  - University of Wisconsin
    - Bankruptcy, [1913] (Box 34, Folder 7 - 8)
    - Insurance, [1913] (Box 34, Folder 9)
    - Negotiable instruments, [1918] (Box 34, Folder 10)
    - Property I, 1902, 1913, n. d. (Box 34, Folder 11)
    - Property II, 1906-1909 (Box 34, Folder 12 - 13)
    - Property III, [1912-1914] (Box 34, Folder 14)
  - Yale University-Commercial bank credit I, 1938 (Box 34, Folder 15)
- Family and Personal Papers, 1875-1948, Series V
  The series is arranged in two sections: Family Papers and Personal Papers. This Series primarily contains correspondence, but also includes diaries, journals, student notebooks and other materials created by or about Moore and other family members including his wife and two children. The Personal Papers section is largely composed of correspondence and related materials between Moore and other family members, while Family Papers generally includes discrete items related to Moore or other family members.
  Family Papers is arranged alphabetically by name of the family member, then alphabetically by subject. Moore's efforts to have his daughter's dissertation published as a book, Cityward Migration, and in obtaining complimentary book reviews for her from his colleagues and friends are well documented. Also included in the Family Papers section are materials created by Underhill Moore's father, Dr. William O. Moore. Prior to Moore's graduation from Columbia University, Dr. Moore had been a successful ophthalmologist with several articles published in medical journals. In addition, there is extensive correspondence relating to the administration of a trust established by Moore's maternal grandfather, Abraham Underhill. Abraham Underhill was a lawyer whose financial successes provided multiple generations of his extended family with significant income from the 1880s through 1940s.
  Although the Personal Papers section is composed primarily of correspondence between Moore and his family members, there is also a diary of his sailing trip to Gibraltar in 1929 and several items from his years as a student at Columbia University. Moore's chronological arrangement of Personal Papers has been largely retained.
  The materials in this section illustrate the sweeping changes in American life from 1906 when Underhill Moore moved to Lawrence, Kansas to begin teaching at the University of Kansas Law School to the early 1940s, his last years in New Haven, Connecticut. Moore's letters to his wife, Henelia Wilhelmi Moore, during their courtship and early years of marriage are particularly expressive and reveal a very different aspect of his personality than shown elsewhere in the collection. The couple's correspondence with each other and friends includes detailed reports of individual and family trips to Europe during the 1920s and 1930s, a diary of Moore's sailing voyage to Gibraltar in 1929, correspondence and receipts documenting the couple's spending habits, and records related to Moore's extensive involvement with his children.
  Moore's influence upon the education and careers of his two children, Alwine Jane Moore and Kent Moore is also documented. These records include Jane Moore's correspondence from Europe during the period from 1931 to 1935 as she continued her collegiate study of economics and gathered statistical data for her doctoral dissertation on migration patterns in Sweden. There is also a substantial amount of correspondence sent and received from Kent Moore while he served in the U. S. Army during World War II.
  The researcher should be alert to the possibility that materials relating to the same topic may be collocated in more than one section and/or series in this collection. For example, materials relating to the administration of the estate of his maternal grandfather, Abraham Underhill, may be found in this Series under "Abraham Underhill estate" and in Series I under the name of the attorney for the estate (Daniel Burke).
  - Family Papers
    - Moore, Henelia Wilhelmi-dance cards, 1907-1913, n. d. (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - Moore, Jane Cityward Migration -publication correspondence, 1938-1939, undated (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - Moore, William Oliver
      - Biographical notices, receipts, photographs, and other items, 1902-1929, n. d. (Box 35, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence and newspaper articles relating to death of William Oliver Moore, 1929-1943, n. d. (Box 35, Folder 4)
      - Financial journals, 1875-1877, 1886 (Box 35, Folder 5)
      - Letters and accounting from John Cabot relating to coca leaves, 1885, n. d. (Box 35, Folder 6)
      - Medical publications, 1894-1908, n. d. (Box 35, Folder 7 - 8)
      - Medical training notebooks, 1870, n. d. (Box 35, Folder 9 - 10)
      - New York City public health visit log, 1881 (Box 35, Folder 11)
      - New York University Law School, 1897, 1900 (Box 35, Folder 12)